<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Deep calleth unto deep, or, A visitation from on high unto the breathing seed of Jacob which is not satisfied among all the professions in the earth, or with the husks cannot fill its belly, but is pincht with hunger, and feels a secret cry for the true bread that comes down from heaven which gives eternal life : wherein is opened some of the mysteries of Gods kingdom ... concerning God ... and concerning Christ ... / by William Bayly.</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25911</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09288391</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09288391</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42615</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27123)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42615)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1301:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Deep calleth unto deep, or, A visitation from on high unto the breathing seed of Jacob which is not satisfied among all the professions in the earth, or with the husks cannot fill its belly, but is pincht with hunger, and feels a secret cry for the true bread that comes down from heaven which gives eternal life : wherein is opened some of the mysteries of Gods kingdom ... concerning God ... and concerning Christ ... / by William Bayly.</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Worship.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42615:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Deep calleth unto Deep;</hi> OR, A Visitation from on High UNTO The Breathing Seed OF JACOB,</p>
            <p>Which is not <hi>ſatisfied</hi> among all the <hi>Profeſsions</hi> in the Earth, or with the <hi>Husks</hi> cannot fill its belly, but is pincht with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and feels a ſecret <hi>Cry</hi> for the <hi>true Bread</hi> that comes down from <hi>Heaven</hi> which gives <hi>Eternal Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is opened ſome of the myſteries of God's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the clear underſtanding of the Poor in Spirit to whom it belongs, but to others it's Parables.</p>
            <p>Concerning GOD, what he is, and where he is, and of his Worſhip; And of the Firſt-day, and the Seventh, or Sabbath day; Alſo ſhewing plainly in what day God is rightly and truly Worſhipped, and the difference and Character of the true Worſhippers and falſe clearly deſcribed.</p>
            <p>And concerning Chriſt, what he was before the Law, and in the time of the Law to this preſent time, and what and where he is now; Alſo ſomething concerning the Word, and the Goſpel, and the Scriptures; and of the Body of Chriſt, and Reſurrection and Aſcention, and of his Coming and Reign, and of the Kingdoms of this World becoming his Kingdoms, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Which may give much ſatisfaction to the upright inquiring mind, being given forth in the true love and compaſſions of my breathing ſoul, that ſo the ſimple might be turned to hear the voice of Wiſdom (which crieth in their ſtreets) and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the fooliſh and live.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Bayly.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>The day-ſpring from on high hath viſited us; to give light to them that ſit in darkneſs, &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 1.78, 79.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>London, Printed in the year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:42615:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42615:2"/>
            <head>A Viſitation from on high, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the fall and, and Reſtoration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF man (who was made upright, after Gods own Image) had never ſinned or tranſgreſſed againſt him; there had been no need of ſacrifice and offerings for ſin, or of a Saviour from it. If man had never fell from the Knowledge of God, and loſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and peace with him, thorow diſobedience againſt his word of command, and ſo become degenerate there had been no need of a reſtoration, reconciliation, or of ſalvation; If man had never gone into darkneſs, out of the right way of bleſſedneſs and everlaſting happineſs, there had been no need of preaching or declaring the way (which is the light) to lead him out of darkeneſs into the way of peace and unity with God again; If there had not been a departure from the inviſible God, who is a Spirit of Truth and Righteouſneſs, then had been no need to ſay to the Sons of men, Return, why will ye dye; If death were not the end of that path which leades from God, the inviſible Fountain of life: If man had never been in bondage and captivity to ſin (and Sathan the author of it,) there had not been need to have mentioned or declared of redemption and freedom from it, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But ſeeing (as the Scripture ſaith) all have ſinned and fell ſhort from the Glory of God, and death hath paſſed upon all men, and darkneſs hath covered the earth, and groſs darkneſs the people, and a vail have been over the face of all nations, and blindneſs hath happened to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo that the Ox and the Aſſe hath more knowledg of their owner than they of the Lord their maker; and all have gone out of the way of peace (which was the good old way before tranſgreſſion was) and the fear of God was not before their eyes as it is written, — and the true voice of God (the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perd)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42615:3"/>hath ſcarcely been underſtood by dream, viſion, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, man hath been ſo degenerate (by the deep ſleep of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, wilfulneſs and perverſneſs) from the pure God and his wayes, that it is hard to be uttered by the tongue of men or Angels, the inviſible eye (that only ſees God) have been ſo blinded, and the wrong eye have been opened, in the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and in the viſibles, that it hath been frequent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the children of men to call good evil, and evil good, to put light for darkneſs, and darkneſs for light; becauſe the God of this world hath blinded the eye; and then by the blind (both leaders and followers) he himſelf is worſhipped as God; even that wicked one which leads out from God, and then exalted himſelf in [man] the temple of God, governing and ruling in the hearts of the children of diſobedience, and this great Whore hath ſate and raigned over Nations, Kindreds and tongues, and the Kings of the earth; and this is that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt whom the Lord will conſume with the Spirit of his Mouth, and deſtroy by the brightneſs of his comming, which day is at hand.</p>
               <p>But now ſeeing (as I ſaid) it is and hath been thus, as before mentioned, all have been concluded under ſin, and in the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of corruption, darkneſs &amp; ignorance, where the myſteries of God and Godlineſs have been hid, and the way of peace not known, being departed from by tranſgreſſion, which is the onely ground of ſeparation between God and man, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is captivated, and become as ſold under it; ſo that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being awakned by the voice of the Son of God, and made alive, and redeemed from tranſgreſſion, and reconciled to God again, man will utterly periſh from Gods comfortable refreſhing preſence, and be for ever driven into darkneſs, where they ſhall never ſee light, but to their perpetual torment and anguiſh this will be the portion of them who knoweth not God, nor deſireth the knowledg of his wayes; therefore there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a Reſtorer, a Redeemer and Saviour, for them who are ſencible of this their fallen, captivated, and miſerable ſtate; for while man is in this ſtate, he neither knows God, nor his vvorſhip; but this inſcription is vvritten upon all their Altars (their prayers, ſacrifices, and vvorſhips; <hi>[to the unknown God.]</hi> for no man knovves the things of God but by the Spirit of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42615:3"/>God, (though they may imagine and talk about them, in their darkned minds,) and none have received the Spirit of God (as to know his doctrine and worſhip,) but they who turns, and have turned at its reproof, (which is in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards parts) which reproofs are becauſe of tranſgreſſion, that it may be turned from, which is the onely ground and cauſe of the ſeparation from God, and of the Ignorance of his will, wayes and worſhip, which is in the ſpirit, and in the truth; which no man can know, or comprehend, or walk in accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, but by the guidance and direction of Gods good Spirit, which is the leader of his Children and people, into all truth and righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>So now ſeeing there is a neceſſity of a Saviour to help and reſtore, redeem and reconcile man unto God again, and of a way to enjoy that happineſs and bleſſedneſs again which was once loſt by diſobedience and tranſgreſſion; And that unity and peace with God muſt again be witneſſed, or elſe all the talk of Hope, Faith, worſhips, or religions, are but in vain; except the Soul (which is in [man,] inviſible and Immortal) comes to enjoy the inviſible eternal God again, in a full, free, true, ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory endleſs life. Therefore it remaines that this Saviour (or the way of this Salvation) be plainly made known, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or charactered to the underſtanding of the ſimple, that the hungerers and thirſters after righteouſneſs, who are weary and heavy laden, may come unto him and be refreſhed; which by the help of Gods good Spirit of grace, (by which it is put in my heart, and brought to my remembrance) I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to do, to that end, and that God may be glorified, being rightly known and worſhipped; in which I have my reward from him and in him, who worketh in me both to will and to do according to his good pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Now this may ſeem (to the wiſdome in ſome) needleſs to treat of, or ſpeak of thoſe things by way of information, directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or doctrine, which have been ſo common and frequently declared and publiſhed in theſe days, in which moſt are ready to ſay (in theſe Countrys,) we are Chriſtians, and beleeve all theſe already, and theſe things have been daily taught in our ſtreets, or the like; and theſe are no new things to our ears, but that which we have heard of old, or from the beginning &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42615:4"/>
               <p> Now mark my words, (and give good heed unto that which followeth,) for they ſhall ſtand faſt (anſwering the witneſs of God in all) as a nail in a ſure place, and they ſhall ſpeak as the oracle of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Concerning the Knowledg of God, His worſhip; and of the firſt day, and the ſeventh or Sabbath day, <hi>&amp;c:</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt as to the matter in hand, at which <hi>I</hi> at preſent aim, is to ſpeak ſomwhat to your underſtandings concerning what God is, and where he is, and what his worſhip is, and where, and how he is to be worſhipped, and by whom he is onely truly and acceptably worſhipped; for this was the occaſion of what follows; or rather the Spirit of God in my heart, took occaſion to give forth theſe things unto publick view, by hearing a diſpute or controverſie between two teachers amongſt the people called Baptiſts neer <hi>Amerſham</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhire</hi>) whoſe names (according to information by enquiry was <hi>Thomas Till<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> &amp; <hi>Joſeph Ciech</hi>) concerning the day or time in which God was to be worſhipped; one ſeeming to hold for the firſt day of the week, and <hi>Tillham</hi> for the ſeventh day; at which time I (being there by chance) had ſpoken ſomething among them of theſe things, if I had not been prevented by being thrown down by ſome of the ruder ſort amongſt them, which was through the occaſion of that <hi>Tho. Tillham,</hi> who ſaid he would not ſtay in the houſe if I was ſuffered to ſpeak amongſt them; and alſo ſaid, that my words came from the Spirit of the Devil, when <hi>I</hi> began to ſpeak in the Spirit of God. So they could do no leſs in obedience to the intent of his words, but to pull me down, or hall me out of the houſe; for he was much in fury, &amp; the mark of Cain I beheld in his face; but I have the vvitneſs in my ſelf, that the bovvels of Gods love in me vvas even yearning to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vvards the ſimple hearted amongſt them, vvhom I ſavv vvere led in ignorance, darkneſs and blindneſs, by their blind leaders vvhich cauſeth them to erre more &amp; more from the vvay of the Lord, by darkning his ſecret counſel (in them) vvith their many words without knowledge, and for their ſakes did the Lord begin to open my mouth in his fear, power, and vviſdom,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42615:4"/>to ſpeak concerning the things that belong to their everlaſting peace, of vvhich novv the Lord have given me an opportunity to write that he may for ever be clear of all their blood, and be juſtified, by them, and this they ſhall acknowledge vvas his love and mercies unto their ſouls in the the day of viſitation, which is at hand hand, vvhether they hear or forbear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Character of true worſhip, and of falſe worſhip, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</head>
               <p>AND now take notice of this one thing follovving, by the way, &amp; conſider it, and the effects of it which hath been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry frequently amongſt the Sons of men, in the cloudy &amp; dark day of Apoſtacy from Chriſt and the Apoſtles life, which is, of worſhipping a God they know not, or without the true knowledge of him whom they worſhip, &amp;c. For in this ſtate and ſpirit hath lodged the very root and ground of all errors &amp; diſcord, ſtrife and confuſion, perſecution and cruelty about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and worſhip, where they have killed and deſtroyed one another about it.</p>
               <p>In this ſtate were the <hi>Athenians,</hi> and the <hi>Shrine</hi> makers of <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> who perſecuted the true worſhippers, who knew the God whom they worſhipped, and declared him unto them, who aroſe up againſt them. Therefore beware of their Altar and inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>[To the unknown God]</hi> whom they did ignorantly worſhip, as many do now, who are in enmity againſt the true worſhippers, who can ſay (to the praiſe of God, as our elder brother did) we know what we worſhip, for ſalvation is of the Jews, (and he is a Jew that is one inwardly.) So the character of a true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is to know God firſt, then to worſhip him in the ſpirit of truth, which only gives that knovvledge: And the character of a falſe vvorſhipper is contrary, vvorſhipping firſt, not knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vvhat, nor vvhom they vvorſhip, vvhich is not accepted, nor [novv] never can be; ſeeing the hour is come that they onely are the true and acceptable vvorſhippers, vvho vvorſhip the Father in the ſpirit, &amp; in the truth; for ſuch onely he ſeeketh to worſhip him, <hi>John</hi> 4: 21, 22, 23, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>To knovv the true and liveing God, is the great and needufl thing vvithout vvhich all vvorſhip, ſacrifice and religion is vain
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42615:5"/>though a man or people had all the words of Scriptures from the beginning to the end, &amp; were in the higheſt profeſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity in the world, yet if he do not truly know God, he is but in darkneſs even until now; and he that ſaith he knowes God, or loves God, and yet hates his brother, is a lyer. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be contented to worſhip an unknown God, or to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip they know not what, is very blind, ignorant, falſe, &amp; erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious; but if thou come firſt to know God, then thou art in the right way of a true worſhipper, as may be mentioned more hereafter; and ſeeing the right way to vvorſhip God, or to be a true vvorſhipper, is firſt to know him vvhom they vvorſhip, therefore it is neceſſary to ſpeak next vvhat God is, (as <hi>I</hi> ſaid before) and then vvhere he is, and hovv he may be knovvn, and then vvhat, and vvherein, his onely vvorſhip is, and vvho are the onely true acceptable vvorſhippers; ſeeing there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny falſe and vain vvorſhips, and vvorſhippers, that knovv not God, nor his day in vvhich he is onely vvorſhipped.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Concerning God, what he is, and where he is, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOD is [Light,] this is our meſſage vvhich vvas from the beginning, and in him is no darkneſs at all, this is his name, he that can hear and receive it let him; vvith vvhom is no variableneſs nor ſhadovv of changing. He is that [<hi>I</hi> am] that ſent <hi>Moſes</hi> to deliver <hi>Jſrael,</hi> to vvhom he ſpake in a buſh, that burned, and vvas not conſumed, but <hi>Moſes</hi> ſavv no ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, onely he heard a voice, and ſo forbad them (by Gods command) of making to themſelves any likeneſs or image of any thing in Heaven or earth, to vvorſhip, (read in the Life of God, vvhich is inviſible,) whoſe voice may be heard, ſaying, To vvhat vvill ye liken me, do not my preſence fill Heaven and Earth; or vvhat houſe vvill ye build for me; and where is the place of my worſhip or reſt? or the day which <hi>I</hi> have ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thorovv out all generations? and this ſame God vvhich ſpake unto <hi>Moſes</hi> vvas the God of his fathers, (vvhich vvere before <hi>Moſes</hi> vvas born, or the Lavv vvritten in Tables of Stone, or the outvvard dayes or Cerimonies vvas) even of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and of <hi>Iacob,</hi> not the God of the dead, but of the living.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42615:5"/>(mark that) and the living it is, that can onely praiſe and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him: he that hath an ear to hear let him hear.</p>
               <p>And this ſame inviſible God, of which no ſimilitude muſt be made, is a Spirit of Light, Life, Truth, and righteouſneſs in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, holy and incorruptible, &amp;c: and ſo is his worſhip in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in the truth, which is witneſſed in the hearts of ſuch as are quickned and made alive by his power and Spirit in their inward parts, who can now ſay to the profeſſors of this age, as our elder brother did unto the women of <hi>Samaria</hi> (though they think themſelves in a better ſtate) for ſhe was then ſaying in her ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity. Our fathers worſhipped in this mountain, &amp; at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is the place where men ought to worſhip &amp;c but he anſwered and ſaid, Woman, believe me the hour cometh, when ye ſhall neither in this mountain, nor yet at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> worſhip the Father, ye worſhip ye know not what, &amp;c. (this is a hard ſaying, can the Jewes and <hi>Samaritans</hi> of our age bear it) God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in the Spirit &amp; in the truth. But ſome wiſe profeſſor might ſay unto me, Who knows not this? But I ſay, be not haſty, or wilfull, but ſtand ſtill and make diligent ſearch in thy own cloſet, and ſee whether thou art yet come to the Spirit, and to the truth (which is but one) (and in it doſt worſhip God,) in which only is the true worſhip; for he that talked with this woman that was able to diſtinguiſh (by her know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) between the way of the Jews and <hi>Samaritans,</hi> telling her all that ever ſhe did, was the very Chriſt (read in the book of thy conſcience) which made her leave her water pot, as he hath many of us (who were as high in knowledge as ſhe) when vve perceived he vvas the Prophet of vvhich <hi>Moſes</hi> vvrote, vvhom all are to hear; that ends the types &amp; temples made vvith hands at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Samaria's</hi> mountain, vvhere their fathers vvorſhipped, &amp;c: but he is to be obeyed novv, vvho ſaid. The kingdom of heaven is vvithin you; vvho drives all his in this path, to vvithin; in the Spirit, and in the truth; for they only knovv vvhat they vvorſhip for ſalvation is of the. Jevves and he is the Jevv that is one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardly: vvhoſe heart is circumciſed to vvorſhip God in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: vvhoſe praiſe is of God, though unknovvn, deſpiſed, or perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted of men.</p>
               <p>So novv I ſay to you, vvho are contending and diſputing about the ſeventh and firſt day outvvardly, in vvhich of thoſe God is to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42615:6"/>be worſhipped, being divided about days, and times, and outward worſhips; one party, for one day and the other part for another day, &amp;c. Not knowing what or which day to worſhip in, like the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Samaritans,</hi> for that was the parallel which came into my heart from God, concerning you both; of which I had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſomthing (as I ſaid before) had you been peaceable like Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or the Church of God, where the firſt is to hold his peace, when any thing is revealed from God to him which ſtandeth by, &amp;c. Which was truly in me, but ſome of you were ſo rude with noiſes (more like Bear-baiters then Chriſtians) that my words ſhould not be heard amongſt you, like them that ſtop their ears and gnaſhed their teeth againſt <hi>Stephen,</hi> which eſpecially was thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that <hi>Tho: Tillham,</hi> of whom <hi>I</hi> was even aſhamed &amp; of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; and indeed my heart could even been broken for you, to behold the blindneſs and ignorance, enmity and wilfulneſs that was amongſt you, which I even marvelled to hear and ſee, in ſuch a (day as this) of Gods revelation and manifeſtation of truth and love amongſt the children of men. But I have conſidered, and ſaid in my heart, how can it be other wayes with you? then it was with Babels builders of old, in confuſion, one building up in this meaning, another throwing down in the other meaning, and Imagination, bringing morter for brick, and brick for morter, not underſtanding one anothers meaning and language; and this is juſt with God, ſeeing many of you have denyed the one pure language (which is before <hi>Babel</hi>) in which God is worſhipped in one conſent; for it is his hand that always breaks and confounds the City, and Tower vvhich the children of men vvould build in their imaginations, vvhoſe top they thought vvould have reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Heaven; This is your ſtate, and the Lord God vvill ſcatter you and your building till there is not one ſtone left upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all the earth; and alſo deſtroy you from being a people, except you repent vvith ſpeed, and turn to him that ſmites you ſecretly, in your conſciences, for your iniquity and hypocriſie; and this is a vvord of propheſie from the Spirit of truth, vvhich ſhall be fulfilled in a ſeaſon that is approaching.</p>
               <p>And novv as concerning your controverſy, about the time or day in vvhich God is to be vvorſhipped, I have ſomvvhat more to ſay, deſiring that you vvould vveigh it in the ballance of equity, though it might ſeem a croſs to ſomthing in you, yet the vvords
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42615:6"/>of my mouth ſhall be right; and the Myſteries of God are in my heart, as a great deep in this matter, which would be very large to expreſs in full concerning theſe things to the clear underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them among you, which indeed cannot be rightly known but by the Keys of <hi>David,</hi> which only opens the door of this treaſury; and though it may be eſteemed a low thing in the eyes of the prudent of this world, and be diſpiſed as a day of ſmall things; yet in this Mountain the Lord have made unto us (his Children,) a feaſt of fat things, praiſe and glory and everlaſting thanks-giving be unto him that ſits upon the throne, and to the Lamb for ever, and ever.</p>
               <p>Therefore now that you may underſtand theſe things, and be rightly informed, mind firſt the fear and dread of the Lord, and be very ſtill and ſerious, with your hear to upright before him, that you may in very dead and truth, perfectly come to know and enjoy the thing that belongs to your Souls everlaſting peace, and read theſe things without prejudice, conſuming envy, which boils in the breſt of that birth which ſhall never inherit Gods Kingdom of Reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Of the Sabbath day.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, take notice, that the [day] in which God [Reſted] was [Sanctified,] who commanded that in it ſhould no manner of works be done, and that they were not to ſpeak a vain word nor think their own thought? either kindle a fire, or bear a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then in that [Day] which was commanded to be kept [Holy.] for indeed it is an [Holy Day] in which God [Reſts,] and in the ſame (In which he Reſted) he dwels for evermore; for he called the [Light] day; and the [Darkneſs] he called night, and ſaith the Scripture, God dwelleth in the [Light,] with whom is no vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs or ſhaddow of changing, and this is the firſt [day] in which he began his Works; and this is the laſt in which he fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes which is Sanctified, [in which he Reſts,] and this is that [Holy Day] in which a man (by Gods command) is forbid to ſpeak a vain word, or think his own thoughts, but this is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery hid from them, in whoſe heart the World is ſo ſet, that they know neither the beginning nor end of the Work of God, for ſaith Chriſt Jeſus by whom the World was made (the beginning
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42615:7"/>of the Creation of God, the end and ſubſtance of the types, days, figures and ſhaddows, who fulfill them, and the law that gave them for their times and ſeaſons.) I am the Alpha, &amp; the Omega, the beginning, and the ending, the firſt, and the laſt; who was before all things, by whom all things were made, whoſe Throne and Kingdome muſt endure for ever; who ſaid [I am] the [Light] of the World, Learn of me, for [<hi>I</hi> am] meek &amp; lowly in heart, and you ſhall finde [Reſt] unto your [Souls;] and this is the ſubſtance of the outward days or Sabbaths; for the word <hi>Sabbath,</hi> is [reſt.] So that if you will be exact in the obſervation of the outward day, (as the Phariſees were, (which was but a figure of the inward reſt,) you muſt onely [reſt] from all manner of Labour, or work outwardly; and yet when that is done, it makes nothing perfect as partaining to the inward conſcience: For the Phariſees judged Chriſt not ſent of God, becauſe (ſaid they) he keepeth not the Sabbath, and ſo in their blind zeal judg him to be a tranſgreſſor, who was the very Subſtance of all thoſe outward things, and is the onely reſt prepared for Gods People, and they who have entred into it, have ceaſed from their own works as God did from his, and ſuch only knowes the [Sabbath day] which is kept [Holy unto the Lord] in which the vain words muſt not be ſpoken, nor the vain thoughts lodg; for the tongue of the juſt (in this day) is as choice ſilver; but the heart of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (which knows neither the beginning nor the end of the works of God) is little worth; but we who have known it, and his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the deep, (upon the face of which the Spirit of the Lord did once move) do know right well, that the ſame [day] in which God began his Works, is the ſame in which he compleats it, and in which he reſted, when he had made all things Good and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; but this is a myſtery to the natural man, or that outward birth that ſticks in the outward natural things, which cannot perceive the things of the moſt inward Spiritual God, and his Kingdom which is within, in the Inviſible hiden man, which is ſpiritual.</p>
               <p>So it is onely the pure in heart that ſees God, and knows his Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and throne, which endureth for ever; where the vain thoughts are judged and caſt out, and not ſuffered to lodg within, for that defiles a man, which is Gods Temple, if the Spirit of God dwelleth in him, whoſe fire is in Zion, and his furnace in Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. Bleſſed is the eye that ſees.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:42615:7"/>
               <p> Therefore if you would rightly know the Myſteries of God and Godlineſs, and of his everlaſting Kingdom of Righteouſneſs and peace, to your Souls ſatisfaction, you muſt enter in by the door, and not clime up another way (as many have done in their ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations) which door is Chriſt, the Light (the Firſt day) that Lighteth every man that cometh into the World, that all men thorow him might believe; and this is the beginning of the work of God, where it is not only given you to believe, but alſo to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for his ſake in whom you have beleeved; in which ſtate you will know the ſix days labour, before the true Sabbath be witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, wherein God reſteth from his Work; for there is no reſt or peace unto the wicked, ſaith my God therefore he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns the ſin in the fleſh, and deſtroys the works of the Devill, in whoſe hand is the Law (which is the School-Maſter to bring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him) who is the end of it for righteouſneſs to every one that believeth muſt needs be the reſt or Sabbath to the ſoul. So his yoke being known upon you, and the daily croſs taken up to the will and wayes of man, in which he hath walked in his own thoughts and vain words, and the bridle to the tongue witneſſed (without which all religion is vain) here you will know ſome work, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtil in awe; in which you wil learn in the lowlineſs of heart, &amp; in ſo berneſs of mind, to put on the Ornament of a meek &amp; quiet Spirit which [in God's ſight] is of great price: and here you may know the [Sabbath day] and alſo the [firſt] in which he moved at the beginning upon the face of the deep, [which is but one] the <hi>Alpha</hi> and the <hi>Omega,</hi> the true and ſaithful witneſs, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the creation of God, who is the end of all things at hand, who ſaith [I am] the [Light] beleive in the Light, and before <hi>Abraham</hi> was [<hi>I</hi> am] He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith.</p>
               <p>So come ye all down to the [door] and enter in thereat (if you would know the ſheep-fold, where he makes his flock to [reſt] at noon which is the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in all your conſciences; &amp; deſpiſe not the [day] of ſmall things, though it be but a ſpark ſhines in a dark place, it is the ſure word of propheſie, to which if you take heed, you wil do wel; it is the teſtimony of Jeſus, which will let you ſee all that ever you do, if you be ſtill, ſtanding in awe and God's fear in your cloſets, our of all reaſonings and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and this muſt you come unto, to know the beginning of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42615:8"/>work of God, even the Light, and Spirit of God, in which the Saints of old began, and in which they walked, and ſaied the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> Ye did run well, who did hinder you, &amp;c? ye begun in the Spirit, and would you now be made perfect by the leſh? and the Spirit is within, and the fleſh is without, Mark, They began in the Spirit, and afterward run in obſervations of days, and months, and times, and parties, who were ſaying, J am of <hi>Paul,</hi> and J am of <hi>Apollo</hi> &amp;c: are ye not now carnall, and walk as men? J am afraid of you (ſaith he) leſt J have beſtowed upon you labour in vain; yet he travels again in birth with ſome of them, that [Chriſt] may be formed [in] them, who is the end of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward days, months and years (the wiſdom and power of God) whoſe years never fails, but is the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever; the beginning and the ending of the Works of God, (which is but one) whom the heart in which this world is, (and the love of it) knows not; though be came into it, and is come into it, and the World was made by him, and for him; and he is before all things; bleſſed is the man that doth witneſs this in his own particular, for ſuch only have the comfort of the Scriptures which declares of theſe things: Therefore come to the Spirit of God (which reproves the vvorld for ſin) and walk in the Spirit, that it may lead you into all truth, and ſhevv you things to come, in vvhich is no occaſion of ſtumbling, or diſputing about dayes or times; meats or drinks, or the like, but you vvill ſee plainly of the Father, and it vvill take of Chriſt (vvhat he did and ſuffered) and ſhevv it unto you, that you ſhall not need to ſay, Whatis this meaning? and vvhat means the other Scripture? and the like; but you vvill (being faithful) be made partakers of his ſufferings vvithin and vvithout, and knovv his death vvhen you are made conformable unto it, bearing in your body his dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that his life may be manifeſt in your mortal fleſh, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This the Apoſtles and Saints did and do vvitneſs, vvho began in the Spirit and vvalks in the Spirit, and vvorſhips God in the Spirit and in the truth; vvho have no confidence in the fleſh, but are <hi>Jewes</hi> invvardly, vvhoſe circumciſion is not outvvardly of the fleſh, but invvard of the heart and of the ſpirit, vvhich the other vvas but a type of, or a ſhaddovv, as vvas alſo the [Seventh] or Sabbath [day] of the [reſt] prepared for the ſeed and heritage of God.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:42615:8"/>
               <p> So if you would rightly know and obſerve the day in which God is only acceptably worſhipped, you come to the Light, which is the firſt day, and in which God dwels for ever, and is the laſt; as it is written, In thy Light ſhall we ſee Light, for with thee is the Fountain of Life, and the ſecrets of the Lord are with them that fear him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant. Now what canſt thou deſire more (O man) then the Fountain of Life? and to know the ſecrets, and everlaſting covenant of his mercies and loving kindneſs, in which is the treaſures of wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg; which are made manifeſt unto them who waits at that wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms gate, which was before the hills was, whoſe voice cryed in the ſtreets to the ſimple, ſaying turn in hither, eat of my bread, and drink of the wine which I have mingled, forſake the fooliſh and live; Therefore take my advice in Gods Counſel, and come now to the fear of the Lord, and wait in his [Light] which makes all things manifeſt, for that is the beginning of wiſdoms path, which leads unto the perfect [day] in which the moſt holy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable everlaſting God is worſhipped; and out of this there is no true knowledge of him, or his worſhip, or any acceptance with him; or any aſſurance; ſtability; or ſatisfaction, which will endure for ever, and this is the word of the Lord unto you all; For the hour is come that the true worſhippers, (who know what and whom they worſhip) do worſhip God in the Spirit and in the truth, theſe are the true worſhippers who worſhip the Father; this is the childrens worſhip, that honours their Father and their Mother, whoſe days are long in the Land of the living, even the everlaſting day which ſprang from on High.</p>
               <p>So all the worſhip and ſacrifice, without the guidance of God's good Spirit of truth is falſe, and they that run, ſtrive, and act with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it are falſe worſhippers, let them profeſs (in words and ſhow) what they will; for the Spirit is the guide of its children, (the true vvorſhippers) into all truth, in vvhich they vvorſhip their father vvho ſeeketh ſuch to vvorſhip him; And all ſuch as are not guided by it, do run before it, and talk of the things of God in their dark underſtanding, &amp; ſenſuality, out of God's covenant of Light, and doubt of his fear, in the contentions and debates, ſtrivings, diſputings, and vain janglings about them, and thoſe things that ſhall for-ever (in that ſtate) be hid from their eyes. So that all people upon earth, in all their profeſſions of religion vvithout the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42615:9"/>leadings of God's Spirit, are at beſt but vvill-vvorſhippers, like <hi>Nimrod</hi> the mighty hunter before the Lord, (and the Lord is that Spirit) the beginning of vvhoſe kingdome is Babel, (confuſion) read your ſtate, vvith God's vvitneſs, the Light in all your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, vvhich vvill anſvver the truth, and do not diſſemble, not ſtrive to make coverings, vvhich vvill be too narrovv? For it is even ſo: The very beginning of that Kingdom, worſhip or building, where the (Spirit) of God is not the guide and leader, is [Babel,] and there the mighty hunter (who is a mighty one in the earthly comprehenſion) goes before the Lord [that Spirit,] which ſhould guide and go before them: But the day is at hand, that <hi>Nimrod</hi> and his Kingdom, (both City and Tower, which was built in the high imaginations) muſt fall; and all the untempered morter-daubers ſhall fall with it, and the wall ſhall be no more at all nor them that daub it, the Life of God hath ſpoken it, which is come down to confound the Language of all the Earth, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them from what they have imagined to do.</p>
               <p>Therefore hear all ye people, in whoſe hearts are any honeſt deſires, or true breathings after the true and living God, and the Knowledge of his wayes and worſhip, come ye all to the [Light] of Chriſt Jeſus, with! which you are Lighted, in which (as you abide) you will come to know the [one pure Language] in which the Righteous Pure God of Truth is [onely] worſhipped, with [one] conſent, which was before [Babel] the many Languages, and before the hunters confuſion and contentions about theſe things was; in which you will come to feel the path of Peace, and way of Holineſs, in which a fool ſhall not erre; where your Immortal Souls may be ſatisfied as with marrovv and fatneſs in Gods Houſe; vvhere the Bread is ſure, and the Water fails not; vvho makes Rivers in the deſert, and the dry Land ſprings of vva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and makes the Wilderneſs a fruitful field, and the barren Womb to bring forth many Children, vvhich are as Oliv-branches round about his Table; Glory unto him that Liveth and Raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for Evermore in the Higheſt. Amen.</p>
               <p>Therefore come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> (confuſion) ſaith the Lord, come avvay and ſtay not, but come into <hi>Zion,</hi> (the Holy Hill) and declare in it the Vengeance of the Lord againſt her: For the Arrovves are ready, and the Bovv is bent by the arms of the Almighty, that ſhall ſink <hi>Babylon;</hi> therefore haſte,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42615:9"/>run, and deliver every man his ſoul out of her; for God hath ſet her on fire at both ends (he that can read let him) and thou ſhalt be burnt, O City of confuſion, the ſmoke of whoſe torment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to aſcend up, which ſhal aſcend for ever and ever; for ſtrong art thou, O Lord God Almighty, who wilt judge and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge thy own cauſe, and of thy righteous ſeed, and the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus upon her, and thou haſt ſaid, the time is at hand that ſhe ſhal ſink like a Milſtone in the depth of the Sea, and riſe no more at all; therefore unto thee be the glory and praiſes, ſongs and halelujahs in the higheſt for evermore, for thou art worthy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ABel</hi> worſhipped God in the Spirit, and in the Truth, but <hi>Cain</hi> was a falſe worſhipper, and knew not God; who aroſe up againſt <hi>Abel</hi> his brother, and killed him about Worſhip. <hi>Enoch</hi> walkt with God and was tranſlated, he worſhipped God in the Spirit and in the truth, and God took him, and he had a witneſs in him that he pleaſed God. <hi>Abraham</hi> obeyed God, who rejoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſee <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s day <hi>(the Light)</hi> and was led out of his own Country thereby; he was a true Worſhipper of God in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in the Truth. Theſe, and many more obeyed God, and vvorſhipped God, and knevv God and his day in vvhich he is vvorſhipped before the Bible vvas vvritten, vvhich declares of theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſau</hi> the firſt Birth, the cunning Hunter abroad, loſt the Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and Bleſſing; he was a profane perſon: but <hi>Jacob</hi> the plain man, the ſecond birth, which carried at home, was bleſſed.</p>
               <p>And ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe mind is ſtaied on thee, thou wilt keep him in perfect peace: But the fooliſh woman her feet abides not in her houſe, but pulls it down with her own hands; being without, loud, ſtubborn and clamorous:</hi> Theſe things were written for your learning, and may be read near, they are an Allegory; but let him that readeth underſtand, for the time haſtens in which they ſhal clearly be underſtood to the ends of the earth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:42615:10"/>
            <head>The Second Part, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Chriſt Jeſus and his Names, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>AS concerning Chriſt Jeſus, what he is, and what he was, and where he is none knows, or can rightly or truly know, but ſuch as have received the Spirit of Truth, which leads in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Truth, and ſhews the things that are, and are to come; which reproves the world for ſin, for righteouſneſs, and for judgment; which is the Comforter of all them who forſake their ſins, their own righteouſneſs, and all falſe judgment, and puts on his righteouſneſs, and righteous judgment, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds that of the Scribes and Phariſees, who in all ages did (and do) ſhut the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, not entring themſelves, nor ſuffer (but perſecute) them that would. And the Kingdom of Heaven is within, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſt is a [Name] given to ſome [thing] which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that [Name] was; and [Jeſus] is a [Name] given to the ſame thing; and <hi>Emanuel,</hi> and many other [Names] are given to the [one] ſelf-ſame [thing] according to the diſcoveries, operations, and manifeſtations unto them, and in them (in ſeveral ſeaſons) who declared of him according as they wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, and knew his appearances, and effectuall workings in their inward parts; even the holy men of God, who ſpake as they were moved by the holy Spirit, which Spirit revealed the Myſteries of Godlineſs unto them according to his will, and their ſeveral meaſures and abilities of his gift.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Chriſt of whom they ſpeak, was in the world before the Law, and in the time of the Law was that myſtery hid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the vails and types, figures and ſhadows, carnal ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ceremonies; in which time he was as a ſeed, (or that good part, or ſubſtance of truth, and righteouſneſs) hid in the conſciences of the Children of Iſrael; which anſwered the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Law written in tables of ſtone. This Moſes ſaw in his day,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:42615:10"/>who received the Laws, ordinances, ſtatutes, judgements and ceremonies, which were to keep them in a ſence, and in a fear towards God, againſt whom they had tranſgreſſed; and to keep them near the feeling of his tender ſeed and witneſs in them, that they might not be wholly hardened againſt his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, when the time came that [he] ſhould be manifeſt to Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, which was the end &amp; ſubſtance of all theſe outward things; Which once being rightly known and obeyed in the inward parts, keeps the heart and conſcience tender and upright, pure and undefiled in God's ſight and fear, without the precepts of men, ſhadows or ceremonies; for I have ſeen that wiſdom of God that gives the interpretation of things, and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the dark ſayings of old, and what was hid in all thoſe Ceremonies in the time of <hi>Moſes's</hi> Laws; and he that makes known the Parable (I am ſure) is the end and ſubſtance of them all; in whoſe Light let me ſpeak of two or three which in ſimplicity hath been hid from the wiſdom of man, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not anſwer them, but as that underſtanding is brought to nought; but let that anſwer in which they are given forth, and you ſhal underſtand them with ſatisfaction; and my que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions are theſe:
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Why did the Lord command, that when any one found a birds neſt, that the Dam was not to be taken with the Young?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>And thou ſhalt not ſeeth a Kid in his mothers milk?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Nor fow thy field with diverſe ſorts of ſeeds?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Nor wear a garment of linnen and wollen together?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>And thou ſhalt not muzle the mouth of the Ox that treadeth out the corn, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Now if thou canſt ſee with that eye which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw (who was a fool for Chriſt) when he ſaid, Doth God take care for Oxen? or, Speaks he not this for our ſakes? For our ſakes, no doubt, &amp;c. Then thou wilt anſwer, Doth God take care for birds neſts? or the ſowing of fields? or garments of linnen and wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len? or Kids, or their mothers milk? or was there not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in all this for our ſakes? Well, but however theſe things ſerved to keep them in a ſence of the unknown ſeed, which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered becauſe of the hardneſs of heart, and corrupt will of man, which had loſt the knowledge and guidance of God's good Spirit, and theſe things ſerved for a time, even till the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42615:11"/>fulneſs of time came, in which the ſeed came to be manifeſt (which was Chriſt) who had been hid from ages and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and till the ſame ſpirit that raiſed up Jeſus from the dead comes to dwell in people, and quicken their mortal bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the power of God vvitneſſed, and the Spirit of Truth to be the guide and leader into all truth, and to be their Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c. But vvhen this is fulfilled and vvitneſſed, there is no more need of any ſhadovv, figure, or ceremony to put us in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, but the Spirit of Truth being received brings all things to our remembrance, and ſhews us things (paſt, preſent an) to come; vvhich declares plainly of the Father, and no more to us in parables, figures, or ſhadows.</p>
               <p>So now, this Chriſt was before the World (that now is) began, and was a ſeed before any <hi>Name</hi> was given to it, which in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time (being begotten of God) was born of a Virgin, had a Body prepared, to do the will of his Father, (as it is at this day) but none knows him (or ever ſhall) <hi>Born</hi> but of a <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin;</hi> (he that hath ears let him hear) whoſe <hi>eye is ſingle, mind ſtayed</hi> on God, forſakes <hi>all,</hi> takes up the <hi>daily Croſs,</hi> denyes <hi>Self,</hi> followes the Lamb whereſoever he goeth; loves him that had been ſlain more then all, more then Father, Mother, Wife, Husband, Children, Houſe or Lands, Yea, of his own <hi>Life;</hi> theſe only knows him <hi>born,</hi> though once like Mary, ſaid <hi>How can this be,</hi> ſeeing <hi>I</hi> know not a man? (ſeeing <hi>I</hi> have no ſtrength, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, parts, or abilities of my own,) but the anſwer is, as it was (be thou but the Virgin) the <hi>Power</hi> of the moſt High ſhall over-ſhaddow thee, and that. <hi>Holy thing</hi> which <hi>ſhall</hi> be <hi>born</hi> of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God; this was Chriſts <hi>Name</hi> in the Womb, <hi>a Holy thing</hi> (read within,) and then had other names, as <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and <hi>Emanuel,</hi> and many more before theſe, and many more ſince, and yet he is but <hi>one,</hi> and was before them all; This is the <hi>I am</hi> which was before <hi>Abraham,</hi> whoſe name in the beginning was the Word, all things were made by him and without him was not any thing made that was made in him was Life and the light was the Light of men &amp;c: <hi>John</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, 4, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Awake therefore now ye ſhepherds, who have been keeping your flock by night: And look upwards ye earthly minded, and behold his Star in the Eaſt, the wiſe men (whoſe eyes are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42615:11"/>in their head) have ſeen it, and been led by it, till the Babe was found lying in a Manger, for in the Inn there was no room for him: He that hath an ear to hear, let him hear, and he that hath an eye, let him ſee, for the day is come, that what we have ſeen in ſecret muſt be preached upon the Houſe-tops. Behold a wonder, a woman doth compaſs a man, and yet ſhe is clothed with the Sun, was there ever ſuch a thing heard? but this is in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and none knowes it, or ever ſhall (as I ſaid) but the <hi>Virgin</hi> who is over ſhaddowed with the <hi>Power</hi> of the moſt High, And this is the word of the Lord God unto all People upon Earth; Therefore if thine eye be ſingle, thy whole body ſhall be full of Light, (and God is Light,) but the double minded man is unſtable in all his wayes, and the Carnal mind is enmity againſt God, and is not ſubject to him, but the <hi>Virgin</hi> is ſubject to the Power of the moſt High, where Chriſt is known to be firſt a holy thing, then a Child given, and a Son born, which is Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel, God with us, a Saviour, a wonderfull Counſeller, the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God the Prince of Peace; with many other names, which (as <hi>I</hi> ſaid before) is given to this <hi>one incomprehenſible being</hi> which the whole world cannot contain. But that which may be known of God, (or Chriſt, which is one is manifeſt <hi>in</hi> people, there he is, and is onely to be found, and he that have ſeen him (who is the Son,) hath ſeen the Father alſo, but it is onely the pure ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle inviſible eye that can ſee him, for he is a Spirit, and is known and worſhipped onely in the Spirit, and in the Truth, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This is that God (which <hi>Paull</hi> preached to the <hi>Athenians</hi>) that made the World and all men of one blood that dwells upon the face of the earth, and hath appointed them bounds of their habitations, times &amp; ſeaſons that they all ſhould ſeek the Lord, if happily they might feel after him, and find him, who is come near to judgment, and is the ſwift witneſs againſt all unrighteouſneſs and ungodlineſs of men, for he ſearches the heart, and tries the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſhews unto man what is his thought: this is he that formed the Mountains, and created the Winds, whom the Heaven of Heavens cannot contain; and yet dwells with him that is of an humble and contrite Spirit, and trembleth at his word, and he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in his people, whoſe God he onely is, who know him dwell in them: And ſaith <hi>David</hi> to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42615:12"/>people, Let God ariſe, and his Enemies will be ſcattered as ſmoke before the Wind, and this is he by whom all things was made, as it is written, <hi>John,</hi> 1 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning the Word, and the Scriptures.</head>
               <p>IN the <hi>beginning</hi> was the <hi>Word</hi> and the <hi>Word,</hi> was <hi>with God,</hi> and the word <hi>was God;</hi> all things were made by him, and vvithout him vvas not any thing made that vvas made; in him vvas life, and the liſe is the Light of men, and the Light ſhineth in the darkneſs, but the Darkneſs comprehendeth it not, &amp;c: Read this now vvith underſtanding, and thou wilt ſee that Chriſts name is called the <hi>Word of God,</hi> as it is vvritten in <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.13. And then if thou comeſt to ſee him the ſeed of the woman vvhich bruiſeth the Serpents head, thou mightſt knovv the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the ſovver, vvhich ſowed good ſeed in the field, in all the ſorts of ground there mentioned, (but the enemy ſovved the tares in the field) and the field is the vvorld (vvhen the parable is opened) and the ſeed is the vvord of God <hi>Luke</hi> 8:11: And ſaith <hi>David, I</hi> have hid thy word in my heart, that <hi>I</hi> might not ſin againſt thee, which vvas a Light to his feet, and as a lamp to his path; and ſaid the Apoſtle, We have a more ſure vvord of propheſie, (then the outvvard voice though it came from the excellent glory) vvhich ye do vvell to take heed unto as unto a Light in a dark place &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Novv this was not the Scriptures, but of this the Scripture declares, even of the vvord which vvas in the beginning, before the Scriptures vvere vvritten, vvhich cannot be properly (in no ſence) called the vvord, or vvord of God, becauſe it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words, &amp; declares of vvhat God did and ſaid, of his Creating the World by the vvord, vvhich vvas not created by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but holy men of God ſpake and vvrit them, as they vvere moved by the Holy Spirit (vvhich is the Word) And ſaid <hi>Moſes,</hi> God ſpake all theſe vvords, <hi>Exod.:</hi> 20: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vvhich <hi>God</hi> vvas the <hi>Word</hi> in the beginning that ſpake the <hi>words.</hi> and the vvord of the Lord came to the Prophets, at ſeveral times, and upon ſeverall occaſions, ſaying, Thus ſaith the Lord, &amp;c: So then, they ſpake and writ vvhat they were commanded by the Word of the Lord: ſo that it is plain to them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42615:12"/>that have a right underſtanding, that the <hi>words</hi> vvere given forth from the <hi>word,</hi> vvhich <hi>word</hi> was hid in their hearts (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith) vvhich vvas there before the <hi>words</hi> vvere given forth; &amp; Holy men of God vvere moved firſt, (by that vvhich is Holy) to ſpeak and vvrite, before they did ſpeak or vvrite forth the Scriptures, vvhich are a true declaration of thoſe things vvhich were done and ſpoken by the <hi>word</hi> which was in the beginning; and Iet none ſay, that the report is the arm of the Lord, ſeeing <hi>Iſaiah</hi> (a true Prophet of God) did make a true diſtinction between the report and the thing reported of; for ſaith Chriſt, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are they that teſtify of me &amp;c: but in him was the life and Salvation, and not in the Scriptures, though they are an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teſtimony, and true declaration; And yet how ignorant have people been ſince the Apoſtles dayes (in the Apoſtacy) of theſe things, calling the Scripture the Word of God, when the Scriptures themſelves ſaith, Chriſt is the Word, and in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning was the Word, and the World was made by the Word; but the Scriptures were not in the beginning, neither was the World made by them; for they are many words ſpoken at ſundry times ſince the beginning, and ſo are many words which declares of the Word, and of thoſe things which are certainly believed among us, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning the Goſpel.</head>
               <p>AND ſo in the time of ignorance and darkneſs (which hath been for ages) both teachers and people who have been and yet are in the Apoſtacy from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Life and Spirit, have frequently called the writings (<hi>of Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> &amp; <hi>John</hi>) the Goſpel, and ſo have called the Scriptures the Goſpell, when as the Scriptures (the true declaration) ſaith, the Gopſel is the power of God, and the Goſpel is everlaſting, and the Goſpel was preached to <hi>Abraham</hi> long before <hi>Marthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> &amp; <hi>John</hi> were born, which Goſpel is the power of God, and Chriſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the power of God, and the wiſdom of God, who ſayd, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> rejoyced to ſee my day, and he ſaw it and was glad; ſo <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> knew the [glad tidings] who was before <hi>Moſes;</hi> for God ſaith to <hi>Moſes,</hi> I am the God of thy Fathers, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob;</hi> this was before the Scriptures, this was the power of God
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42615:13"/>and the wiſdom of God, by which the ſoul immortal comes to be redeemed, the captive delivered, the chaines of darkneſs death, and hel broken, and all its enemies ſcattered; this is glad tidings indeed, and this is rightly called the Goſpel of ſalvation, of which <hi>Paul,</hi> nor we, are not aſhamed; for it is the power of God, and many have the Scriptures, and yet have not ſalvation or redemption by them, but are in the errour, ignorance and darkneſs, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God, of which the Scriptures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares.</p>
               <p>And in this ſtate people have been in great contentions, and debates; ſtriving in their dark imaginations about theſe things, and can never be ſatisfied, nor never ſhall, till they come to the Light in themſelves, which only can give them the knowledge thereof; for that is the Key of <hi>David,</hi> that opens to [them] who do not exerciſe themſelves in things too high for them, but are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as weaned children; for ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> wiſdom is to high for a fool, and ſhe dwelleth not with conſuming envy, neither wil ſhe enter into a froward heart; for wiſdom is a loving Spirit, ſhe is the beginning of all the works of God; and the fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdom; unto which if a man comes not, he ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know Gods ſecrets, nor the myſteries of his kingdom, which are hid to that part, nature, or Spirit in man, that would always be knowing and climing up into the tree of knowledg, and would know the myſteries (but not obey his call, and come down as <hi>Zachens</hi> did) but the Croſs is to obey according to what is already known, though it be never ſo little of ſtature; and without this daily Croſs (which croſſeth the haſty mind, the wil and wiſdome of man) there can be no true knowledg of the Myſteries and will of God, and without it, thou can never know true peace and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, though thou compaſs ſea and Land in thy comprehenſion, the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning the body of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>AND now having mentioned ſomthing concerning Chriſt, and concerning the Word, and the Scriptures, and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There is ſomwhat in my heart remaining concerning the body of Chriſt; about which great contentions, opinions and debates have been amongſt them, whoſe eyes are not in their head,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42615:13"/>but at the ends of the earth. Firſt, I beleive (and we beleive) that Chriſt had a body, and came and preached, and ſuffered, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and roſe, and aſcended, and ſitteth at Gods right hand, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> According to the Scriptures; but yet ſome are ſaying to us (with a lying Spirit) You deny the Reſurrection, and the body of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which (for the ſimple-ſake according to the Scriptures of truth) I ſhall anſwer:</p>
               <p>As for Chriſt, I do beleive in my heart infallibly, that he had a body prepared him to do the will of God, and that he ſuffered the contradictions of ſinners in the days of his fleſh, and was crucified by wicked men, great profeſſors, chief prieſts, rulers, Souldiers, and elders; and was laid in the grave, and roſe again according to the Scriptures, and did aſcend over all the principalities and powers of the darkneſs of this world, and now ſitteth at the right hand of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>I</hi> do alſo beleive, that he hath yet a body which was prepared, and is yet preparing to do Gods will, in earth as it is in heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But me thinks I hear ſome ſay (in their reaſonings and imaginations) What body hath he? and where is it? ſeeing it is ſayd, he is at the right hand of God; this I ſhall anſwer with his own words, which he ſpake here on earth, <hi>viz.</hi> No man aſcended up into heaven but he that came down from heaven, the Son of man which is in heaven; he that hath an ear to hear, let him hear, and take notice, what body that was which come down from heaven, when Mary ſayd unto the Angell; How can this be, ſeeing I know not a man? when he told her the Saviour ſhould be born, and that holy thing that ſhould be born of her, ſhould be called the Son of God; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now mark the anſwer, The [power] of the moſt high ſhall overſhadow thee, by which [power] the body was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared here on earth, and ſaith Chriſt (the Saviour, the wiſdom of God, and the power of God) a [body] haſt [thou] prepared [me] mark the diſtinction, [thou] [me] and [a body] this [me] that ſpake in the [body] was the [Chriſt] which had a [body] prepared to do [his] will that prepared it: Now was it the [body] or an inviſible power, Spirit or Soul, that ſayd, A [body] haſt [thou] prepared [me] He that hath an ear, and underſtanding, let him hear, and judge.</p>
               <p>But yet here this queſtion may riſe concerning the body of Chriſt; is it not written, The heavens muſt contain him untill the reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42615:14"/>of all things? And was he not taken up into heaven, when the cloud received him out of the ſight of the <hi>Gallileans</hi> that gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned outwardly after him! To this alſo I may anſwer (unto thee who lookeſt dayly for his perſonall appearance and coming?) if the heavens muſt contain him until the reſtitution of all things; why doeſt thou thus ſo much expect his coming before that time of the reſtitution of all things? or canſt thou ſay, that that time is come; if not, let it come firſt, before thou ſo earneſtly expect his coming; but indeed it is but a cloud that hath received him out of the fight of the gazers; but ſaith the Lord (to his children) I have blotted out your iniquities like a thick cloud, and to the people, your ſins have ſeparated between me and you, and have with held good things from you. And indeed this hath hid both his body and face from you; for the kingdom of heaven, and the Lord from he aven comes not with outward obſervation, but the kingdom is within, and the Lord from heaven is that quickning ſpirit which quickens them that have been dead in the ſins, &amp; the treſpaſſes (the clouds of ſeparation,) that they might live unto God, and behold the beauty of the Lord in his temple; which temple they are in whom he dwells, and in whom he walks, and he is their God, and they are his people; and the day being come, and the Sun riſen, the clouds and the ſhadows are fled away; but they who live in iniquity are dead unto God, whoſe God he is not, the cloud is ſtil between, that they can neither ſee darkly as in a glaſs, nor face to face, but are in darkneſs, clouds &amp; blindneſs even until now.</p>
               <p>But if the inquiſitive mind be not yet anſwered, but art ſtill ſaying as they did in the Apoſtles days concerning the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction How doth the dead riſe? and with what body do they come? I muſt anſwer unto thee as he did, Thou fool, that which thou ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt it not that body that ſhall be, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the Lord giveth every ſeed it's own body as it pleaſed him; It is ſown <hi>A naturall</hi> body, but it is raiſed a <hi>Spirituall</hi> body; It is ſown in weakneſs, but it is raiſed <hi>in power,</hi> a <hi>Spirituall</hi> body, raiſed <hi>in power;</hi> now canſt thou tell what body this is; But if thou underſtand it not, thou haſt little or no knowledge of the myſteries of God, I ſpeak to the ſhame of that inquiſitive mind, that would know theſe things which are hid in Gods treaſury; and yet will not come to the door, nor the keys that gives the un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42615:14"/>of them; without which no man can enter this Kingdom (which is prepared for that birth to which only it be longs) for no man knoweth the things of God, but by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, which ſearcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God, which are ſpiritually diſcerned: So that unleſs you come to the Light and Spirit of God (the door) that reproves the World for ſin, and lets you ſee the evil of your wayes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, enduring the croſs, and bear the condemnation and in dignation, becauſe you have ſinned againſt the Lord, and turn at his reproofs, that he might powr forth his Spirit upon you, and make his words and ſecreta known unto you; I ſay, unleſs you enter in this way at Gods Light and Spirit that ſhines in your hearts, you ſhal never rightly know, underſtand, or enjoy any of theſe things (of Gods Kingdom) before mentioned, it's, an infallible word of Truth from God unto you all. For they are hid perpetually from the out-birth of the wiſdom of this World, and revealed onely to the Babes in the inward ſpiritual ground in Chriſt Jeſus, who is ſtill a myſtery hid to the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, Scribes and Phariſees, rulers, elders, and hypocrites, as wel in this age, as in the ages paſt, who then were ſaying among themſelves (notwithſtanding his mighty works which were done among them) Is not this the Carpenters Son, whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother we knew, and are not his brethren and ſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers among us; &amp;c. Undervaluing and contemning his low and mean appearance (who was in the forme of a ſervant) and theſe did love to be called of men Maſter, and greetings in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and upermoſt Rooms at Feaſts, and to go in long robes and ſtand praying in the chief or higheſt places in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and were the blind Phariſces to whom the woe belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as at this day it doth to them who in the ſame ſpirit are contemning the low appearance and manifeſtation of the Son of God, ſaying, Is not this (you preach or declare of) which people muſt believe in natural Light, even this which checks and reproves us for ſin? Have we not had this alwayes with us from our child-hood? and do not we know its father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her? Is it not ſome of the remainder that was left in <hi>Adam</hi> after he fell; to reſtrain him and his children from groſs evil &amp;c. And is it at beſt any other then reſtraining grace, and not ſaving? or but natural conſcience, and the like? this hath been
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42615:15"/>the reaſonings amongſt many, though mighty works hath been done, and are yet a doing, and muſt yet be done by him (who is the Light, the Power, the Grace, the Truth, and the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God) in theſe laſt days thorowout the earth.</p>
               <p>But O ye Children of men, and high in the tree of Knowledg (which is forbidden as to ſeed upon) let me anſwer theſe your reaſonings with a few queſtions in Gods Wiſdom, which is hid from the eyes of the prudent of this World, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What was that ſeed, and where was it, after man fell (which was promiſed) that it ſhould bruiſe the Serpents head? And what is that Serpent, and where is he, whoſe head muſt be bruiſed?</p>
               <p n="2">2. What was that which let <hi>Adam</hi> ſee his Nakedneſs when he had tranſgreſſed?</p>
               <p>What are the Eyes of the Lord that are in every place, behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the evil, and good; and where are they if not in every conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſeeing the Lord ſaith to his faithful, I will guide thee with mine eye?</p>
               <p n="3">3. And what is the true Light that Lighteth every man that commeth into the World; and what is that Light of men that ſhineth in the darkneſs (which the darkneſs comprehendeth not) and where is it, if not in the conſcience of every man?</p>
               <p n="4">4. What grace is that, and where is it, which hath appeared unto all men, which bringeth ſalvation, which is the Saints teacher; is it onely reſtraining, and not ſaving? ſeeing the Scripture ſaith it bringeth Salvation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. What Light is that of which the body ſhall be full, if the eye be ſingle? and what is that ſingle eye, or the one eye with which it is better to go to Heaven, then with two into Hell-fire? and what is that eye which is the Light of the body, ſeeing the eye of the Lord is the guide?</p>
               <p n="6">6. And what makes the difference between the wiſe Virgins and the fooliſh? and whether the Lamp without oyl, and the light burning, be not the form or profeſſion without the power and life which ſaves from ſin, and gives an entrance into the everlaſting Kingdom of God?</p>
               <p n="7">7. What wiſe man is that (which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of) whoſe eyes are in his head? and what is that fool vvhoſe eyes are at the ends of the earth?</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:42615:15"/> 8. And vvhat is that prudent man, which foreſees the evil, and hides himſelf? and what did he hide from? and in what is the ſure hiding place, and what gives the fore-ſight of evil? what is that fool vvhich paſſeth on and is puniſhed? and vvhat is the head of every man?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whether the fear of the Lord be not the beginning of Wiſdom, and to depart from evil be not underſtanding? and vvhether they vvho are not yet come unto the fear of the Lord (vvhich is to depart from evil) be yet come to the beginning of true vviſdom; and if not yet come to the beginning, it is poſſible they may be the fools vvhich may dye for vvant of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if they do not ſpeedily repent and turn to him that ſmites them for their folly, &amp;c. So take this for an anſvver till thou knovv further, of vvhich much might be ſaid, and of this kind, but a few vvords to the vviſe may be enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Chriſt ſecond coming, and Kingdom, and Raign; and of the Kingdoms of this World becoming his Kingdoms.</head>
               <p>I Never read in all the Scriptures (as I can remember) of a third comming of Chriſt perſonally, in his ovvn fingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or of a perſonal reign beſides vvhat ſhall be in his Saints. But I have read of his coming the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation &amp;c. which the Apoſtles in their days did witneſs; yea, even his comming and Kingdom as may be mentioned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. <hi>I</hi> believe moſt people (in that called Chriſt endom, who have read the Scriptures) will confeſs Chriſt is come once al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, even when he had the body prepared which he laid down and took up without the gates of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> this <hi>I</hi> grant was a perſonal comming, or the God head dwelt in that perſon bodily, this we conclude was his firſt comming to be manifeſt in theſe days; and we beleive all the things that are written of him to be really true; and that whatſoever he did or ſaid muſt be fulfilled, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But now this being his firſt comming, he tels his diſciples while he was yet with them, that he muſt go away, and that it was expedient that he ſhould go away, or elſe (ſaid he) the Comforter will not come, the vvhich if I go avvay I ſhall ſend unto you, even the Spirit of truth, vvhich ſhall abide vvith you
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42615:16"/>for ever, &amp;c. Yet notvvithſtanding ſorrovv had filled their hearts, though he tell them he vvould come again unto them, and their heart ſhould rejoyce, and their joy no man ſhould take from them; This vvas his promiſe to his diſciples, vvhile he vvas yet perſonally vvith them; and to comfort and ſtrengthen yet more, he told them, that he that vvas vvith them ſhould be in them, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For they loved his perſon for the ſake of the frame &amp; quality of the ſpirit that dvvelt in him; or elſe vvhat vvas his perſon (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mean and contemtible) to them, more then another perſon, but for that vvhich dvvells in him they loved him; let none miſtake, I do not ſlight it, nor the perſon of any of his brethren, or children, as they are prepared to do the vvill of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but I do knovv in Gods Counſel that it was even ſo, as it hath been alſo in theſe days among vvhom God the Father of mercies hath as it were deprived ſome of his diſciples of the perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal preſence of ſome of his dear ſons &amp; ſervants, which may be to this end, that the ſame Spirit and Life might be felt, poſſeſſed, lived in, &amp; enjoyed in themſelvs, in their own particulars, in which onely their eternal well being conſiſteth,</p>
               <p>And ſo he taught them to pray, <hi>Our Father</hi> &amp;c. Not to look at his perſon, and pray to him as a perſon without them, but bid them pray to their Father which ſeeth in ſecret, who would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them openly; and he that ſeeth in ſecret, ſearcheth the heart, &amp; trieth the reins: &amp; he bid them pray, <hi>thy Kingdom come,</hi> &amp; the Kingdom of Heaven is within, and the heart and reins and the ſearcher of them is within; And he bid them wait at Jeruſalem till they were endued with power from on high; &amp; the Kingdom of God conſiſteth in power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So they waited for his comming and Kingdom in their days after his bodily departure from them, and alſo came to enjoy what they waited for, and to receive the promiſe of the Father, which was fulfilled unto them, and in them, For ſaith the Apoſtle, we wait for his Son from heaven; this was after he had ſuffered and was departed from them, and at length ſayd, the Son of God is come, and hath given us an underſtanding that we know him that is true, and are in him that is true, this is the true God and eternall Life, and this Life is in his Son; And then again ſpake on this wiſe, Wee have received a Kingdom which cannot be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; letus have grace in our hearts whereby we may ſerve God
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42615:16"/>acceptably with reverence and godly fear; for our God is a conſuming ſire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So here they received the Kingdom, and the Son of God was come, &amp; they vvere in him, vvho came unto them in his Kingdom: Here vvas Chriſts prayer ſulfilled, vvho ſaid, That they might be one, as vve are one; thou in me, and <hi>I</hi> in them, and they in me, that vve all might be perfect in one; and here is their prayer alſo fulfilled, or anſvvered, vvho ſaid the, <hi>thy Kingdom come, &amp;c.</hi> When they receive the Kingdom vvhich could not be moved; vvhich Kingdom Chriſt tels them was vvithin, ſo this they received &amp; vvitneſſed, which was the ſecond time unto ſalvation from ſin, who never mentioned (as ever I need) of a perſonal coming and reign the third time, or of a third coming in a ſingle perſonal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, as hath been imagined by many, who know not the wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be endued with power from on high, but a running in their ovvn vvils and times, and vvill-vvorſhips, and feigned humilicies, vvhich is not at all accepted vvith God, vvhile that birth is not being, nor that body prepared, vvhich only can do his vvill acceptably. But <hi>this</hi> we have read, of the pourings forth of the Spirit in the Laſt days upon all fleſh (then none is excepted) and Sons and danghters ſhould propheſſe, (which is come to paſs) and that the Lord will come in ten thouſands of his Saints to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince all the ungodly of their ungodly deeds and hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him, and to execute his judgements, (this is comming to paſs) and that he will conſume Antichriſt by the Spirit of his mouth, and deſtroy him with the brightneſs of his comming (then not with carnal weapons, but withſpiritual he will deſtroy Antichriſt) &amp; when this is done, then muſt the Kingdoms of this world needs become his, and he ſhall Reign for ever, and ever. Bleſſed is the eye that ſees, and the heart that feels and underſtands theſe things, for the time is born, and the day is dawned in which they ſhall be fulfilled; And this is the Word of the Lord of Heaven and Earth, who is come to Reign, and reigneth, and vvill reign till all his enemies are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his footſtool; and the Kingdoms of this world become his Kingdoms and dominions even for ever &amp; for evermore. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the earth tremble, and them that fear and obey him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce; Amen, <hi>Hallelujah:</hi> Amen,</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:42615:17"/>
                  <l>O Thou profeſſor, who are yet a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſor,</l>
                  <l>Would'ſt thou know the Myſteries of God, thou muſt firſt feel his Red,</l>
                  <l>Which will thy back ſunce till thou leave works of night</l>
                  <l>And walk in the Light, this is the way to know the firſt day,</l>
                  <l>And alſo the reſt, which is Holy and for ever bleſt.</l>
                  <l>For Zacheus climbing was too high the Saviour to embrace,</l>
                  <l>But down below he was received in whom Salvation was;</l>
                  <l>The voyce, that from the tree did call, (though below him) he obeyed,</l>
                  <l>The little ſtature is not deſpis'd, therefore be not afraid.</l>
                  <l>But come then down into the houſe, with joy the Light receive,</l>
                  <l>For he's the Saviour of all men that in his name believe.</l>
                  <l>The tree of Knowledge hath beguil'd and fed the birth muſt dye,</l>
                  <l>The tree of Life hath not been known while in the wiſdom High.</l>
                  <l>Men have aſpired, and not deſired with poverty and thirſt,</l>
                  <l>To walk i'th Light, with hearts upright the plain path of the juſt;</l>
                  <l>Therefore the Pearl from them is hid who dig not in the deep.</l>
                  <l>But with the ſluggard and the fool in rags and folly ſleep.</l>
                  <l>But now the awakning day is come the trump aloud doth ſound.</l>
                  <l>The Life's reveal'd as in days paſt mans wiſdom to confound.</l>
                  <l>Therefore all people ſtand up and ſee the ſtate in which you are,</l>
                  <l>For either Heaven, or hells your Lot the hour is not far,</l>
                  <l>For I have heard from throne of God a dreadful voyce and cry,</l>
                  <l>O England, England, thou art viſited and now thy end draws nigh.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Even ſo haſten thy Work O Lord God Almighty, as thou haſt ſhewed thy Servant, and cut it ſhort in Righteouſneſs for thine Elect ſake that cries unto thee night and day thotowout the whole Earth. Even ſo come Lord Ieſus, come quickly, ſaith my Soul. Amen.</p>
               <p>Written by a Servant of the living God, who is a trembler with joy at the VVord of his Power, for whoſe ſake I am in outward bonds, at <hi>Hartford;</hi> but my peace can no man take from me, bleſſed be the Lord (the God of Jacob) whoſe compaſsion fails not, but his Mercies endures for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W.B.</signed> 
                  <date>The Second <hi>Month,</hi> 1663.</date>
               </closer>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:42615:17"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
